<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Recent Discussions</title><link>https://planet.crystal-lang.org/</link><description></description><item><title>Loading ECR templates at runtime*</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/loading-ecr-templates-at-runtime/8546</link><author>willhbr</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 06:58:19 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[I’ve been doing a bit of a dive into how ECR works, and ended up implementing a way to reload the non-code parts of ECR files at runtime. This means you can make an HTML template, tweak styles/layout and see the changes immediately, so long as you don’t touch any Crystal code in the template.Once I knew how ECR works (it’s really cool!) I realised I could load the template-y parts of the ECR file at runtime, which gives me most of the benefit of runtime templates while still being able to compile to efficient code (sans hot reloading) on a release build. That post also has a bit of explanation on why ECR is so cool.Hopefully someone finds this useful or my explanations interesting!]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>New shard, kemal-controller</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/new-shard-kemal-controller/8545</link><author>hugopl</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 19:03:27 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[I’m used to the rails way of doing a MVC web applications, so every time I was doing something with Kemal I had the felling of missing something, yes, a controller class.This shard does that, it add a way to write Kemal routes in a controller class (struct in fact), but the most interesting thing it does IMO is to map the HTTP/Route parameters into method parameters, example:struct UsersController < Kemal::Controller
  @[Get("/users")]
  def index
    "Listing all users"
  end

  @[Get("/users/:id")]
  def show(id : Int32)
    "Showing user with ID: #{id}"
  end

  @[Post("/users", auth: true)]
  def create(name : String, age : Int32, description : String?))
    "Creating user with name: #{name}, age: #{age} and description: #{description}"
  end

  private def authenticate! : Bool
    true
  end
end
Not a single release yep, API isn’t stable but may not have radical changes, meanwhile I’m using it in a not yet released project to test the API.]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Hot ECR Reloading in Your Area</title><link>https://old.reddit.com/r/crystal_programming/comments/1ozgsxh/hot_ecr_reloading_in_your_area/</link><author>/u/sdogruyol</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 13:51:10 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://old.reddit.com/r/crystal_programming/">r/crystal_programming</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>OptionParser : conditional option</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/optionparser-conditional-option/8544</link><author>hutou</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 18:43:14 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[Hi,
In OptionParser, would it be possible to have an option B depending on another option A, giving an error if option A is missing?]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Hello, Crystal Community 👋🏼!</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/hello-crystal-community/8543</link><author>omarluq</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 05:53:34 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[I’m Omar, a Senior DevOps Engineer in Austin, TX. I spend most of my days in the Kubernetes and Go world, so picking up Crystal has been a really refreshing shift, especially since I’ve always been a Rubyist at heart.I recently started hacking on a minimalist terminal I/O library for building TUI’s in Crystal, and I’ve been having a great time with it. This language is seriously a joy to use.Excited to learn, share, and meet everyone here.]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>