<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Crystal News Planet</title><link>https://planet.crystal-lang.org/</link><description>Liveboat RSS Feed</description><item><title>Wanna visualize your crystal code?</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/wanna-visualize-your-crystal-code/8554</link><author>ralsina</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 16:29:02 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[A while back I mentioned what I called the Ralsina Programmatic Universe, a chart I kept of how each of my projects used other projects and so on.It was a pretty half-baked thing …WELL now it’s AT LEAST 75% baked!And here is a fun thing: if you are a github user, you can get yours with no effort! Just:You can click on a repo to focus on it and its dependencies, you can search for a specific repo, double clicking will open the repo in the browser.]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Get the current mode of a file</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/get-the-current-mode-of-a-file/8553</link><author>Fulgurance</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 16:35:44 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[Hi guys, I have a question. Is there any way to get the octal value (mode) of a file in crystal ?]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>A minimal terminal API shard omarluq/termisu</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/a-minimal-terminal-api-shard-omarluq-termisu/8549</link><author>omarluq</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 04:30:52 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[I’m building Termisu, a small, minimal terminal API inspired by Termbox and Termbox-Go. The goal is to offer a simple, lightweight foundation for building text based UIs on *nix systems.I don’t use Windows myself, so cross-platform support isn’t on my immediate roadmap, but I’m open to contributions if anyone wants to explore that side.If you’d like to try it out and give feedback or suggestions, I’d really appreciate it!]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Gatekeeper</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/gatekeeper/8547</link><author>henrikac</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 21:01:46 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[I’ve just released a small shard called , and I wanted to share it here in case it’s useful to others. is a lightweight .
It doesn’t try to be a full security framework — instead, it focuses on one thing:Enforcing  for your routes, using whatever authentication mechanism  choose.It integrates into any Crystal HTTP handler chain, evaluates your rules, runs your authenticators, and returns  or  when needed.Simple  (regex path matching + optional HTTP methods)
– sessions, JWT, API tokens, whatever fits your app with a built-in Optional Customize responses for
Only ~125 lines of actual logic — intentionally tiny and focusedrequire "gatekeeper"

class AppHandler
  include HTTP::Handler

  def call(context)
    case context.request.path
    when "/"
      context.response.print "Hello World!"
    when "/admin"
      context.response.print "Hello admin!"
    else
      context.response.status = HTTP::Status::NOT_FOUND
      context.response.print "Not found"
    end
  end
end

# Configure Gatekeeper
Gatekeeper.config do |config|
  # Called when no authenticator can produce a user
  config.on_unauthenticated = ->(ctx : HTTP::Server::Context) do
    ctx.response.print "You must log in first."
  end

  # Called when a user exists but lacks the required roles
  config.on_unauthorized = ->(ctx : HTTP::Server::Context) do
    ctx.response.print "You do not have permission."
  end

  # Only allow users with role "admin" to access /admin
  config.auth_rules << Gatekeeper::Rule.new(
    /^\/admin/,
    roles: ["admin"]
  )

  # Allow everyone to access everything else (no roles)
  config.auth_rules << Gatekeeper::Rule.new(/^\//)

  # Simple authenticator that always logs in an "admin" user
  config.authenticators << ->(ctx : HTTP::Server::Context) : Gatekeeper::Identity? do
    # In real code you’d look at cookies / headers / session etc.
    Gatekeeper::IdentityUser(Int32).new(1, Set{"admin"})
  end
end

handlers = [
  Gatekeeper::AuthHandler.new,
  AppHandler.new,
]

server = HTTP::Server.new(handlers)

address = server.bind_tcp "0.0.0.0", 3000
puts "Listening on http://#{address}"
server.listen
This is , but the API is stable, fully tested, and intentionally small.
I plan to iterate slowly with community feedback (rule helpers, role hierarchies, route attributes, etc.).Any thoughts, suggestions, or ideas are very welcome!Edit: Renamed kemal-guardian → GatekeeperEdit: Updated the example]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Loading ECR templates at runtime*</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/loading-ecr-templates-at-runtime/8546</link><author>willhbr</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 06:58:19 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[I’ve been doing a bit of a dive into how ECR works, and ended up implementing a way to reload the non-code parts of ECR files at runtime. This means you can make an HTML template, tweak styles/layout and see the changes immediately, so long as you don’t touch any Crystal code in the template.Once I knew how ECR works (it’s really cool!) I realised I could load the template-y parts of the ECR file at runtime, which gives me most of the benefit of runtime templates while still being able to compile to efficient code (sans hot reloading) on a release build. That post also has a bit of explanation on why ECR is so cool.Hopefully someone finds this useful or my explanations interesting!]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>New shard, kemal-controller</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/new-shard-kemal-controller/8545</link><author>hugopl</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 19:03:27 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[I’m used to the rails way of doing a MVC web applications, so every time I was doing something with Kemal I had the felling of missing something, yes, a controller class.This shard does that, it add a way to write Kemal routes in a controller class (struct in fact), but the most interesting thing it does IMO is to map the HTTP/Route parameters into method parameters, example:struct UsersController < Kemal::Controller
  @[Get("/users")]
  def index
    "Listing all users"
  end

  @[Get("/users/:id")]
  def show(id : Int32)
    "Showing user with ID: #{id}"
  end

  @[Post("/users", auth: true)]
  def create(name : String, age : Int32, description : String?))
    "Creating user with name: #{name}, age: #{age} and description: #{description}"
  end

  private def authenticate! : Bool
    true
  end
end
Not a single release yep, API isn’t stable but may not have radical changes, meanwhile I’m using it in a not yet released project to test the API.]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Hot ECR Reloading in Your Area</title><link>https://old.reddit.com/r/crystal_programming/comments/1ozgsxh/hot_ecr_reloading_in_your_area/</link><author>/u/sdogruyol</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 13:51:10 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://old.reddit.com/r/crystal_programming/">r/crystal_programming</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>RE: https://ruby.social/@willhbr/115564828622296517[1]</title><link>https://fosstodon.org/@CrystalLanguage/115564893854977349</link><author></author><category>official</category><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 11:52:18 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://fosstodon.org/@CrystalLanguage">@CrystalLanguage</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[Neat enhancement for ECR that allows hot reloading of static strings in the template at runtime 🤯 Changes to the Crystal code still require rebuilding, but this reduces the feedback loop for little changes such as adding a class in an HTML template.]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>OptionParser : conditional option</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/optionparser-conditional-option/8544</link><author>hutou</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 18:43:14 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[Hi,
In OptionParser, would it be possible to have an option B depending on another option A, giving an error if option A is missing?]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Hello, Crystal Community 👋🏼!</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/hello-crystal-community/8543</link><author>omarluq</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 05:53:34 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[I’m Omar, a Senior DevOps Engineer in Austin, TX. I spend most of my days in the Kubernetes and Go world, so picking up Crystal has been a really refreshing shift, especially since I’ve always been a Rubyist at heart.I recently started hacking on a minimalist terminal I/O library for building TUI’s in Crystal, and I’ve been having a great time with it. This language is seriously a joy to use.Excited to learn, share, and meet everyone here.]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Single Crystal Graphene: the 2 Dimensional super material for space elevators</title><link>https://www.azom.com/article.aspx?ArticleID=16371</link><author>dreadsword</author><category>HN</category><category>hn</category><pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 17:11:28 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://news.ycombinator.com/newest">Hacker News - Newest: &quot;Crystal&quot;</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[In this interview, Adrian Nixon, CEO of Nixor Ltd, talks to AZoM about Space Elevators and how 2D materials will contribute to them.How does a space elevator work?The concept is straightforward. At the moment the only way of getting into space is to ride on a rocket. However, there is another way.Imagine you are standing at the equator. A geostationary satellite has been launched into orbit right above you. From your point of view, that satellite will always be directly above you.Now, imagine that you could drop a cable from the satellite down to the ground. You would see the cable directly in front of you. You could grip the cable, start climbing and eventually, you would climb all the way up into space. That’s it.Even though the concept is straightforward, actually doing it is quite the opposite. It will be one of the major engineering challenges of all time, but graphene could help.It sounds like science fiction! Could a space elevator really be built?When I first heard about the space elevator I thought it was science fiction too. Then I looked into the background and I discovered there is a worldwide community of very credible engineers and rocket scientists who believe this can be done and they are actively working on the technology.Back at the turn of this century, NASA decided to find out whether this was a realistic project.  The NASA Institute for Advanced Concepts (NIAC) funded a feasibility study into the Space Elevator, using one of their most respected scientists, Bradley C. Edwards. Dr. Edwards conducted a thorough six-month investigation and reported back with findings based on an assessment of the challenges involved and the key components of the technology:There are four basic elements of a space elevator.The base station and anchor.The counterweight and orbital space station.The tether (the cable that connects the surface to space).The climber (the elevator carriage).Dr. Edwards found that given enough money and time, everything apart from the tether could be created with the current technology. There was no material strong enough to make the tether. Carbon nanotubes were proposed as a candidate material but no continuous production process has emerged that can make them in the quantity and quality needed.So, the whole space elevator project effectively stalled. However, a global group of highly skilled rocket scientists and engineers kept alive the idea in an organisation called the International Space Elevator Consortium (ISEC). They maintain a constant watch on developing materials science.Since the NASA report was commissioned, a new material has been isolated - graphene. The technology of graphene is maturing and it now has the attention of ISEC as a candidate tether material.What are the main challenges making Graphene materials for Space Elevator tethers?Image Credits: Rost9/shutterstock.comGraphene is a fantastic 2D material. It is 200 times stronger than steel, transparent, flexible and conducts electricity better than copper. However, graphene can only be made commercially in little bits with the current technology.Take for example, the ‘200 times stronger than steel’ property. You can't make full use of that at the moment because the current commercial state is to produce graphene from graphite using the top-down method. This makes graphene as nano plates that are typically 400 nanometers long. To give an idea of how small this, look at the edge of a piece of copier paper, which is 100 microns (100,000 nanometers) thick. You could fit 250 of these graphene nanoplates across the edge of that piece of paper.So, you can see graphene nanoplates really small. You can imagine that if you wanted to use the current commercially available graphene for a space elevator task, and lots of other applications, you're going to need something like a chain. You've got all these really strong small links, but they're not connected together so nanoplate graphene will not work.The first solution you might consider would be to glue together the nanoplates. Research has been carried out looking at copolymerizing graphene nanoplatelets with various polymers to make a strong composite, however, this is not strong enough to be a viable tether material.The other way of making graphene is by the bottom-up method, which assembles graphene, atom by atom. The leading technology is called Chemical Vapour Deposition (CVD). Even though this process is really still in its infancy from an industrial point of view, it is impressive.The CVD process usually involves heating methane and hydrogen to just below 1000 degrees centigrade over a clean metal surface, such as copper or nickel. As the hot methane approaches the surface of the metal, a reaction takes place catalyzed by the metal that removes the hydrogen from the carbon in the methane molecule. The carbon from the methane lands on the metal surface and starts to link up with other carbon atoms. The lowest energy structure is a flat sp2 hybridized carbon - in other words, graphene. Once the surface is covered, the reaction stops, leaving a one atom thick 2D covering of graphene on the metal.You would think you would have a continuous sheet of graphene across the surface, but you don't get a perfect layer because there are some problems. One, is that the surface of the metal contains cracks at the microscopic level, (it looks a bit like crazy paving). When the graphene layer grows over that, it often picks up these discontinuities and you will get defects in the sheet.Another problem is that graphene grows from multiple spots at the same time; a bit like snowflakes landing on a pavement. These form separate domains, which gradually increase and then butt up against one another. Again, you get discontinuities. This creates polycrystalline graphene.Having made the graphene layer, you now have to remove it from the metal. There are two basic approaches. The first is to dissolve away the metal using an etchant solution such as a strong acid or oxidizing agent. The second is to use a strong sticky tape. The sticky tape method usually leaves a polymer residue that contaminates the graphene.Both methods are currently a batch process, although teams in the UK, USA and Norway are working on turning this method into a continuous process. All of these methods are still in the laboratory phase at present.Image Credits: 30000ad/shutterstock.comHow can you make Graphene suitable for space elevator tethers?The tether needs to be as strong as possible, so this means the entire length of the structure needs to be made from single sheets of graphene that are defect free. Such a structure would be a single molecule at a macro scale. Until recently this was thought to be impossibleHowever, back in January and March 2017, I proposed a continuous process for making defect free sheet graphene in rolls.Things then started to get really interesting, because later that year (in the summer of 2017) a team at Peking University announced they were the first to make near perfect graphene at a scale of 500mm x 50mm. They called this material single crystal graphene. A crystal in this context refers to a repeating regular pattern, rather than the sparkling brittle crystals of our everyday experience.Single-crystal graphene is important because it is very strong. Tensile strength is a measure of the force needed to pull apart any material and is measured in Pascals (Pa). Commercially available structural steel has strength of 550 MPa (550 Million Pa). A space elevator tether needs to be made from a material with strength of at least 50GPa (50000 MPa), so steel is not strong enough. Single-crystal graphene on the other hand, has a tensile strength of 130GPa. (130000 MPa). It is the strongest material ever tested and will be strong enough to make a space elevator tether.To answer your question, single-crystal graphene is the material that can make space elevator tethers. That material exists. It has already been made in the laboratory.As nothing like a space elevator has ever been made, how much can you theoretically and practically test it?NASA has done a great deal of the theoretical work on the elements of the space elevator. The International Space Elevator Consortium (ISEC) and others have continued this work so we know where the space elevator could be built and many of the obvious technical challenges have been thought through and addressed.As far as single crystal graphene is concerned we are still at the early stages. We know the material has been made at a laboratory scale but samples have been isolated for further testing.A few weeks ago, in May 2018, a team in South Korea made near perfect single-crystal graphene at the centimetre scale for testing in a laboratory. They measured the strength directly and found that the sample had a Young’s modulus of 0.9 TPa. This is very close to the predicted value of 1.0 TPa and establishes graphene as the strongest material ever tested.If you want to find out more, I’ll be presenting about this and more at the ISEC conference in Seattle on the 17th August 2018.How close are we to constructing the real thing?Image Credits: chombosan/shutterstock.comThe space elevator is about to enter the public consciousness; in simulation anyway. Disney announced a few days ago that they are now working on a Space Elevator simulator to an orbital restaurant at Disney World’s Epcot Centre in Florida!Arthur C. Clarke famously said the space elevator would be built fifty years after everyone stopped laughing. The laughter has already stopped. The real thing could be closer than you might think. A proof of concept project will be necessary to show that single-crystal graphene can be made by a continuous process. Then a series of follow up projects to design and make the production machines, so that the process can be optimised and scaled up properly. The ISEC team estimates it will probably take about 20 years. It will cost approximately 20 billion dollars just for the tether.To actually build all of the other elements, it would probably cost another $80 billion. We could get it to completion for somewhere under 100 billion dollars, over a 20 to 30 year period. That figure compares with the global space industry that is worth around 360 billion dollars in 2018 alone.You probably would discover all sorts of interesting things going forward as well, because the ROI on all this is just staggering. It might even happen in my lifetime, however there are still many hurdles to overcome.I wouldn’t want to give anybody the impression that it's going to happen anytime soon. At the moment this is a set of ideas - they've been well thought through, but they need testing properly.  This will be an industrial strength challenge over an extended period of time but I’m convinced this can be done.How will the space elevator benefit us, and what do space elevators mean for the future of space travel?Apart from getting us into space smoothly and safely, the operating costs are low. At the time of writing you can expect to pay around $20,000 per kilogram to take a payload into orbit, but with the space elevator, once you've paid all the setup costs, then you are down to $100 or $200 per kilogram. Even with large set up costs the business case is compelling.It makes a lot of sense with the return on investment (ROI) over a long period of time. If you're just going to use it as a one off, then it's a very expensive onetime thing, but the idea is that once you get a space elevator built space travel becomes routine and cheap.Dr. Edwards summed up the implications in his report for NASA: “…the long-term return we (humans) would receive on the construction of a space elevator is staggering, it would literally change our world.”Beginning his career as a Chartered Chemist and Member of the Royal Society of Chemistry, Adrian Nixon is now the Senior Editor at InvestorIntel and the Founder/CEO of Nixor Limited. He is also an advisory board member of the National Graphene Association and the Co-Founder/Facilitator of the Foresight Forum.Adrian Nixon will be the keynote speaker at the 2018 International Space Elevator Conference (17th-19th August 2018); held at the Museum of Flight in Seattle, Washington.
        Disclaimer: The views expressed here are those of the interviewee and do not necessarily represent the views of AZoM.com Limited (T/A) AZoNetwork, the owner and operator of this website. This disclaimer forms part of the Terms and Conditions of use of this website.
    ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>File reads, reversing a slice</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/file-reads-reversing-a-slice/8542</link><author>BloodFeastMan</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 22:01:10 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[Playing with file reads / writes, so this loop will read from an input file and write to an output file:loop do
	buf = Slice(UInt8).new(4096)
	n = infile.read(buf)
	break if n == 0
	outfile.write(buf[0...n])
end
All is fine, the output file hashes correctly.If I place a  in there:loop do
	buf = Slice(UInt8).new(4096)
	n = infile.read(buf)
	break if n == 0
	buf.reverse!
	outfile.write(buf[0...n])
end
.. and run it twice, first on an input file, and then on the file that the first run produced, I would have thought that I would be back to my starting point, but the final result (after running it twice) does not hash correctly, and the contents are jibberish.If I then manually count the input file size and set the  accordingly:loop do
	read_length = do_length(fsize)
	buf = Slice(UInt8).new(read_length)
	n = infile.read(buf)
	break if n == 0
	buf.reverse!
	outfile.write(buf[0...n])
	fsize -= read_length
end
if infile_size < 4096 # infile_size counts down in the above loop
	read_length = infile_size
else
	read_length = 4096
end
Now it will give me my expected result, i.e., if I run it twice, once on an input file and that on that output, I’m back to the same hash as the original input, which is interesting, as only the last slice read would not be 4096, furthermore,   be an exponential growth of 8, i.e., 1024, 2048, 4096, as a random multiple of 8 will give trash results. As an example, 3072 does not work.This snippet doesn’t actually do anything useful, just an interesting observation from a hobbyist, and  I’m sure there’s an explanation.]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Tracking Down Progressively-Enhanceable APIs in Crystal&apos;s Stdlib</title><link>https://willhbr.net/2025/11/07/tracking-down-progressively-enhanceable-apis/</link><author>straight-shoota</author><category>HN</category><category>hn</category><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 17:48:58 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://news.ycombinator.com/newest">Hacker News - Newest: &quot;Crystal&quot;</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[Something that I’m a big fan of is APIs that can be easily modified and hacked with. It’s frustrating to have to write fully production-ready code when you actually want to just prototype something, and so I’m happy when there’s an API that it’s easy to use, which then progresses into a more full-featured API.In Crystal an example of this is . If you want to get the entire contents of a file you can just do:Will this cause problems if the file is huge? Probably, but it works fine for a prototype or in something less critical. Then when you want to be a grown-up and do things properly, the API doesn’t actually change that much:What I didn’t know is that there are a more of these APIs hiding in the Crystal stdlib that I wasn’t aware of. I found these after I captured a profile of my status page library, it’s plenty fast enough (especially because I’m the only person ever sending requests) but I was interested to see what it spent its time doing.I captured the sample using samply which is super convenient. I built it from the main branch so I could use the  flag. This dumps the symbol info directly into the profile file, since running a local web server and having the Firefox profiler talk back to it runs into all sorts of security roadblocks, especially when it’s not actually running locally.To get some nice juicy data, I wrote another little program that would just spam a certain URL with HTTP requests, compiled with  to make the most of my cores:Unsurprisingly, after getting the profile I can confirm it spends its time dumping bytes into the response buffer, since there’s no interesting calculation on my default  page. However there were two interesting sections that were taking more time than I expected.The first is , which replaces characters that could be interpreted as HTML tags with the corresponding HTML entity. I noticed two things, first it immediately calls into , and inside that there’s a  call. My first thought was maybe it’s implemented with a regex that’s convenient but not performant, but looking at the docs and the code, that’s not the case, it uses a  to make replacements with by looking up each character in the string with its replacement in the hash.The  revealed the real issue though,  takes a string and returns a new string with the escapes applied, and that new string has to be allocated. In my code I took that string and immediately dumped it into an :Look at that, I’m using the wrong API! That’s convenient, but it would be better if  would write directly into  instead of allocating its own buffer. Well that’s what HTML.escape(string : String, io : IO) does, and it’s trivial to swap:Re-profiled, and that section is gone from the trace. Easy.Removing the non- API isn’t a good move here, since you’ll just encourage people to do this:Since what they  right now is a , not a lecture about why not to allocate short-lived buffers.The second thing that stood out were calls to IO::Memory#increase_capacity_by.  is a dynamically-sized in-memory buffer, and the default capacity (as of Crystal 1.18.2) is just 64 bytes. When a write would exceed the size of the buffer, the capacity is increased to the next power of two with , so as soon as we write our 65th byte, it’ll be increased to 128 bytes.The response of a somewhat small status page is just under 5000 bytes,  so—assuming a bunch of small writes to the buffer—it will have to be expanded seven times. Since we know the response is going to be at least a few kilobytes (the template with no content is 1kB), setting the initial size to 4kB avoids having to do 6 reallocations.In the end this is a non-issue, because the code is so low-traffic and already very performant. As I’ve written before I don’t like the somewhat superstitious approach of limiting language features because someone might mis-use them. Slow code can come from anywhere, and you have to actually look for it. You can see the changes I actually made to the status page library in this commit.On the other hand, there is an opportunity for languages to enable library authors to guide their API use. Most languages have (either builtin or through a linter) a way of annotating that the return value from a function shouldn’t be ignored. In Rust this is the  tag.What could be neat is a system for attaching metadata to objects at compile time that could be read later in the compile step. So the  method could attach a bit of information that says the string it returns could be directly written to an . Then if that object is passed to  (or  or whatever) it could check that attribute and provide a warning.This would fit in with Crystal’s existing macro system, but I’m sure it would explode the complexity of the compiler and make compilation much slower.]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Restricting options in CLI app</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/restricting-options-in-cli-app/8541</link><author>hutou</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 11:36:09 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[A CLI app I am working on has the following syntax in the command line:appname command subcommand argsI’m using OptionParser and I’d wand to restrict some option at app level or the command level, for example:appname --option1 command  --option2 subcommandso that I’d prevent option1 to be used after command or subcommand, and option2 used before command.]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>VS Code Ameba Extension v0.3.0 Released</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/vs-code-ameba-extension-v0-3-0-released/8540</link><author>nobodywasishere</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 03:26:33 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[What's Changed

Add link to documentation by @nobodywasishere in #146
Move to CancellationToken, Use spawn instead of exec, Add output channel for logging by @nobodywasishere in #147
Reload diagnos...]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Zeroing in on Zero-Point Motion Inside a Crystal</title><link>https://physics.aps.org/articles/v18/178</link><author>lc0_stein</author><category>HN</category><category>hn</category><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 21:17:04 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://news.ycombinator.com/newest">Hacker News - Newest: &quot;Crystal&quot;</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Crystal Forge: Compliance-First NixOS Fleet Management</title><link>https://crystalforge.us/</link><author>UlyssesZhan</author><category>HN</category><category>hn</category><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 19:59:48 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://news.ycombinator.com/newest">Hacker News - Newest: &quot;Crystal&quot;</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Crystal 1.18.0 Is Released</title><link>https://crystal-lang.org/2025/10/14/1.18.0-released/</link><author>ksec</author><category>HN</category><category>hn</category><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 05:25:28 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://news.ycombinator.com/newest">Hacker News - Newest: &quot;Crystal&quot;</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[We are announcing a new Crystal release 1.18.0 with several new features and bug
fixes.This release includes 172 changes since
1.17.1
by 31 contributors. We thank all the contributors for all the effort put into
improving the language! ❤️Below we list the most remarkable changes in the language, compiler and stdlib.
For more details, visit the full
changelog.We do not expect any breaking changes in existing code. If you notice any
unexpected issues, please let us know in the issue tracker or forum.Execution contexts from RFC 0002 continue as a preview feature with opt-in
with compiler flags -Dpreview_mt -Dexecution_context. It might move out of
preview in the next release.The preview of synchronization primitives in  has seen some
improvements as well.Deprecation warnings are now available on types and aliases (#15962) as well
as individual method parameters (#15999).
Deprecated types only trigger warnings when they are actually  (e.g.
calling a class method), not when they’re just part of a type restriction, for
example.
Deprecated parameters only trigger a warning when the particular parameter is
used in a call. Calls without this parameter are unaffected.The format of  has been adjusted slightly to align with the Internet
Extended Date/Time Format (IXDTF) defined in RFC 9557 (#16039).Changes from the previous format:Replace  location by  offsetSkip zero nanoseconds entirely even when  is true (see https://github.com/crystal-lang/crystal/pull/16039#discussion_r2250863021)Remove whitespace between time and offsetWrap location in square brackets to indicate an IXDTF time-zone suffixSome examples show the differences:The local Windows system time zone now uses the canonical IANA name (#15967).The output of  got a wrapper to indicate
the  type and differentiate from the wrapped type (#15979).
The equivalent for  is still pending.The private constructors of  moved into the 
hook (#16147). They’re now defined on the including types which is more robust
in terms of  overload ordering. This also allows referring generic
type variables inside converters. now uses scoped ANSI reset codes which only reset the respective
property, instead of resetting  (#16052).We added type restrictions to many API methods. This improves the documentation.
This is a semi-automatic effort, assisted by a tool that automatically extracts
typing information from the semantic analysis of a program (#15682).Multi-line strings containing source code in compiler specs have had two
different formats: Some of them were using regular string literals, others used
heredocs. The latter was usually preferred in new code additions because
line numbers and indents are more sensible. And with an appropriate heredoc
identifier to denote the language, we even get nested syntax highlighting.
In this release we’ve converted all compiler specs to use heredocs
(#11291).With the help of , we’ve enabled and applied a couple more linter rules:
 (#16010),  (#16011), and
 (#16014).The compiler can dump type information to a JSON file when the environment
variable  is set (#16027).Resolve types when guessing return type from class method overloads (#16118).In the following snippet, the compiler is able to infer ’s type to be , since both overloads of  have a return type of :Guess instance variable types from global method calls (#16119).This allows the following to compile:The call needs to be global; other than that, type guessing for top-level methods has the same limitations as for class methods.Hash literals are evaluated from left to right, fixing a regression from 1.6.0 (#16124).Temporary variables are now grouped by file name in order to increase the chance
of reusing previous macro expansions (#16122).Fully exit the process on  from REPL (#16171)Fixed interpreter hanging on the signal pipe (#16167)Support for LLVM 21.1 and 22.0 (#16062)Update Unicode to 17.0.0 (#16160)We have been able to do all of this thanks to the continued support of
 84codes and every other sponsor.  To
 maintain and increase the development pace, donations and sponsorships are
 essential.  OpenCollective is
 available for that.Reach out to crystal@manas.tech if you’d like to
 become a direct sponsor or find other ways to support Crystal. We thank you in
 advance!Contribute]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Kemal 1.8.0 is released! Faster Routing and Better Error Messages</title><link>https://old.reddit.com/r/crystal_programming/comments/1oqo5wc/kemal_180_is_released_faster_routing_and_better/</link><author>/u/sdogruyol</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Fri, 7 Nov 2025 07:33:52 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://old.reddit.com/r/crystal_programming/">r/crystal_programming</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Question about inheritence</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/question-about-inheritence/8538</link><author>Fulgurance</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Thu, 6 Nov 2025 15:26:24 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[Hi guys, today I did this small test for the need of my project.I would like to understand why the result is false ?class Mother

    def self.isDaughter : Bool
        return self.class == Daughter
    end

end

class Daughter < Mother
end

puts Daughter.isDaughter
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Zensical – A modern static site generator built by the Material for MkDocs team</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/zensical-a-modern-static-site-generator-built-by-the-material-for-mkdocs-team/8534</link><author>Fryguy</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Wed, 5 Nov 2025 16:43:21 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[We are thrilled to announce Zensical, our next-gen static site generator that addresses and overcomes the technical limitations of MkDocs]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Eliminate environment modifications</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/eliminate-environment-modifications/8533</link><author>straight-shoota</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Wed, 5 Nov 2025 09:10:48 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[Modifying a process’ environment is generally not thread-safe because it is memory shared between all threads of a process.
System functions like  or  are based on a global variable ( on unix systems). When a thread updates the environment configuration, it may reallocate the memory. Thus, any other thread which had previously obtained the pointer before the update and is now reading from the old memory, may be left with corrupt data.We could offer some mitigation by synchronizing access through Crystal’s  interface.
However, that would still not be 100% safe because it cannot account for direct access via the system APIs.But maybe there’s a simpler solution: Disallow environment modifications, i.e. deprecate .This idea is based on this hypothesis:Unless your process is a shell or adjacent, it shouldn’t need to mutate its environment.We’d need to look a bit more closely at specific use cases, but I think this might be a valid option.It should be feasible to keep the functionality of  available in a portable interface, but with an explicit warning that it’s potentially unsafe (e.g. ).Safe usage could only be guaranteed in a single-threaded process. It should be safe to set environment variables at the start of a multi-threaded process, before it spawns any other threads.A common usage pattern is when you need to adjust the environment for a piece of code that you cannot configure directly but depends on environment variables.This is primarily relevant for testing code that is supposed to react to environment settings. For example, we test several features in the standard library and compiler using the  helper.
This functionality seems reasonable and relevant.
But instead of modifying the process’ environment, we could mock it using a fiber-local overlay in the  interface.
In some cases, it might even be sufficient to just pass in configuration as explicit arguments.I’m not aware of any specific other use cases. But I could expect instances where you need to modify the environment for calling a library methods which are not using Crystal’s  interface and thus  to read from the actual process environment.
That generally smells like bad design, but there might be some use cases.I’m posting this thread to ask for feedback and examples.29 posts - 10 participants]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Yet another spin-off shard: ralsina/docopt-config</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/yet-another-spin-off-shard-ralsina-docopt-config/8528</link><author>ralsina</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Mon, 3 Nov 2025 15:44:59 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[I like using docopt in my CLI tools because it means the docs are always correct. However once you want to support other means of config like config files and env vars, docopt has no support.UNTIL NOW with ralsina/docopt-config where you get it all for free. Just write your docopt and use docopt_config instead of docopt and It Just Works.Zero config. A simple flat yaml file with keys like your options. Env vars with a prefix and the same name as your options. All that is read and properly prioritized, keeping your docopt as the only source of truth for your app’s config.It’s not for every tool (git would not be a good fit!) but for reasonably simple things it should be nice and easy.]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Lucky is Lightning Fast!</title><link>https://dev.to/kinvoki/lucky-is-lightning-fast-3m2c</link><author>kinvoki</author><category>blog</category><pubDate>Mon, 3 Nov 2025 06:34:05 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://dev.to/t/crystal">DEV Community: crystal</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[: Lucky Framework (Crystal) ranks near the top in TechEmpower Benchmark #20, competing strongly against full-stack frameworks like Rails, Phoenix, and Django.Pretty solid result! Especially if you only consider "Full-stack" frameworks and not micro-stuff.1. Lucky is near the top in Crystal-land (and beyond)In the Crystal ecosystem, Lucky ranks near the top. And in the broader web framework landscape too.2. Crystal frameworks dominate speedThe main speed-competitor in Crystal-land is Raze framework (which has been retired). Lucky's speed is comparable to most other Crystal frameworks: Kemal, Spider-Gazelle, Onyx & Amber (all did pretty well on speed thanks to Crystal 😊)3. Lucky holds its own against full-featured frameworksThe most important comparison for me is against true full-featured frameworks like Rails, Hanami, Phoenix, Django, Symphony, Grails, Spring, Prologue, etc. And  is doing really well there.If you go to the main page, there are ~250 benchmark results for every web-framework under the sun. However, that's too many results for my taste 😊 i.e. things like "h2o.cr" on the list are too purpose-specific for me or anything I would do in a normal course of things, developing an enterprise or user-facing web application.I'm currently considering a Full-Stack Framework for a small web-based enterprise-type project and deciding between Phoenix, Lucky & Rails. Each has its own strengths for my use-case. So this particular comparison is more of an interest to me, based on frameworks & languages that I've had exposure to or would even consider for such an application.
  
  
  ⚠️ Take These Benchmarks with a Grain of Salt
Not all frameworks are properly optimized - Some frameworks on the list may not be configured for optimal performance - Performance should be one consideration among many - Ecosystem, dev experience, and productivity are all more important than speed in most cases ☝️ - Lucky ticks all 3 boxes for me: February 9, 2021Originally published: February 08, 2021 • Last updated: February 09, 2021]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Through the Crystal Ball of VC Florian Graillot</title><link>https://insurtechamsterdam.com/public/blog/insurance-innovation</link><author>Venesha</author><category>HN</category><category>hn</category><pubDate>Sun, 2 Nov 2025 09:12:22 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://news.ycombinator.com/newest">Hacker News - Newest: &quot;Crystal&quot;</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[Today, we sit down with Florian Graillot, a leading voice in the insurtech ecosystem and Founder of AstoryaVC, a specialist venture capital fund dedicated to transforming the insurance industry. 

Florian shares his perspective on how Insurtech has evolved — from early digital distribution models to today’s AI-driven, B2B, and embedded solutions. He discusses the changing expectations for startups and how collaboration between incumbents and innovators is shaping the next phase of insurance transformation.Looking back at the first wave of Insurtech, what stands out most—the successes, the failures, or the lessons that shaped where the industry is today?That’s a very fair question as the hashtag InsurTech recently turned 10 ! Based on all investments announced across Europe in insurance technology, I’d say there are several trends to keep in mind.The first one is that most startups from that initial wave of InsurTech were addressing the ‘distribution’ part of the value chain. Since inception, over half of all rounds announced were in that section. Most players were even distributing directly to end customers (B2C or B2SME) while another significant part of funding went to full-stack players (startups operating under an insurance license).Since the second half of 2022, things have changed.Investors are currently fueling a broader range of startups, either embracing different distribution models (e.g. ‘embedded insurance’) or addressing other sections of the value chain. I think about the ‘product’ part where more startups are leveraging technology to build resilience and tackle emerging risks (including climate or cyber for instance). And a growing number of players have embraced a B2B positioning, meaning they are developing technology for incumbents.Ultimately, several leaders have emerged as the VC market has pivoted from “growth at all costs” to “profitable growth”. Several startups have indeed reached profitability while they have reached great milestones. There are several players on the market with over 500,000 customers - even close to 1m ! -, generating hundreds of millions of Gross Written Premium per year. In the UK, I think about Marshmallow selling car insurance in the UK ; I France I would refer to Alan selling health insurance, Acheel a multi-product full-stack InsurTech or Descartes Underwriting doing parametric weather (and cyber) insurance ; in Germany, Getsafe is selling many B2C insurance products.Long story short, the first wave of insurance innovation is very biased towards two single business models (D2C and full-stack) while several players have clearly emerged, and insurance innovation is more business diverse than ever, getting closer to the insurance core engine.As incumbents increasingly integrate AI-driven underwriting and claims automation, do you see space for pure-play Insurtech disruptors, or is the future more about partnerships and embedded models?AI is a buzzword. But it’s also a reality. Since the beginning of this year, a third of all deals announced in InsurTech Europe were AI-first players ! There are two trends currently structuring the market. Several players are doing “AI in insurance” and building a product or use-case while teaming up together with their insurance customers & partners. Other players are focusing on a single use-case. In the first scenario, we see shorter sales cycles but I’m wondering how to demonstrate a clear RoI with unclear use-case scenarios (up-front). In the second category, sales cycles are similar to those enjoyed in Enterprise software but the RoI can easily be demonstrated as the value proposition is clearly detailed upfront. Let’s see if both categories remain on the market or if one takes the lead in the near future. Anyway, incumbents do initiate many AI projects and there is a real diversity in terms of business models. Almost all of the value chain is under threat. Though, claim management is the clear leader. Underwriting and product design are a growing trend though less players are active on these sections of the value chain (so far).From your vantage point, what are the most pressing risks Insurtechs should be tackling today—regulatory, technological, or macroeconomic? And how do new challenges like electric vehicles, cyber threats, climate change, and digital assets shift that risk landscape?I see three major challenges for insurers in the near future. The first one is how to keep growing while inflation is going down (assuming it led to a massive price surge in the last few years, which drove revenues growth). The second challenge is around operational efficiency. Many players are even raising it publicly. And technology could definitely help. Many B2B InsurTech are already offering their services to incumbents ! Last but not least, new risks are emerging and threatening existing business lines or unlocking new ones. I think about climate, cyber, the switch to electric vehicles, financial fraud & sams, health wellbeing & longevity.Home insurance has become unprofitable in some markets due to climate risk. How can technology help insurers keep coverage affordable while remaining sustainable as businesses?In the US for instance, several players have indeed left local markets. This is not sustainable. Neither in an economic standpoint - revenues are down for these players - nor societally speaking - how to live in a non-insured World ?! In addition, in Europe for instance, several players faced a tough financial year when natural catastrophes pilled while they had a great financial year when the climate was smoother. Such a dependence on climate & natural events, is not sustainable either for incumbents. This is probably why we are spotting so many players exploring how technology (data, algorithms) could help better understand, assess and price these risks. I’m even wondering if, in several locations, climate insurance might become a must have on top of - or instead of - home insurance. And beyond pure insurance it might be a matter of expanding the risk value chain with prevention, risk assessment and resilience.2021 was the peak for VC funding in Insurtech, followed by a steep drop mirroring Fintech and VC globally. How has this climate changed the way startups should position themselves? And what separates those able to raise late-stage capital from those that stall after early traction?You’re right, the VC market has pivoted from “growth at all costs” to “profitable growth”. Startups need to show figures earlier in their journey and should demonstrate their capacity to make money. This may sound obvious but it’s challenging in the insurance industry. First, you need to sell insurance in a profitable way meaning that premium generated should cover claims with a margin ! Then you need to distribute these products - or a tech you have developed - in a profitable way, meaning you should earn more than what it costs you to find customers. Ultimately, a company could consider being profitable if other expenses enable it.Whatever the positioning (selling technology to incumbent or selling insurance products to end customers) startups now need to keep that in mind and not necessarily reached profitability in the short term - investors are here to finance the first customers - but demonstrate they have a resilient business model !Are you seeing a shift in how Insurtech VCs evaluate customer acquisition models—particularly in the SME space where conversion cycles are longer and more costly?I would refer to the famous CAC/LTV ratio in the VC industry. This compares potential revenues (LTV) with how much it costs to sign these customers (CAC). And, as mentioned above, both startups selling insurance or technology should think this way and demonstrate their resilience in that background. The SME space might sound particularly challenging as it combines downfalls: small customers - compared to Enterprise customers - but still professional players, meaning a long sales cycle (compared to B2C). But startups selling insurance to SME - or operating in the SME insurance space - have long been a model in the InsurTech space : regularly there are new entrants, and at a later stage, +Simple is now under Private Equity ownership !Where do you see the greatest impact of Insurtechs on insurers: driving revenue growth, reducing operating costs, or lowering claims expenses? Which of these areas still holds the most untapped potential?Things have evolved over the years. In the D2C space, InsurTech 1.0 claimed it would replace incumbents. If several players have reached significant milestones, things are more balanced and we see more partnerships between corporates and startups.In the B2B space, things have always been more balanced. A lot has been explored in claim management - targeting operational efficiency, but fraud is a regular use-case too (which has an impact on claim expenses. And the more the ecosystem matures, the more startups get close to the insurance core engine (risk assessment & pricing). This might have an impact on the loss ratio.In addition, tech-enabled MGA are leveraging technology (data, algorithms, …) to better address vertical niches. These players may be growth opportunities for insurers they are working with.Overall, tech startups have various impacts on the insurance business. Which makes sense as every section of the value chain and every business line is under innovation threat. There is nowhere in the market where startups are not exploring how to improve - or revamp - how insurance is done !Europe’s Insurtech scene is often described as dominated by France, Germany, and the UK. Which other regions or markets across the continent are underestimated right now?Actually the InsurTech ecosystem is vibrant across Europe. It’s true the UK and France are clear leaders - in terms of rounds announced - while Germany is slightly below what it should be (based on the FinTech comparable for instance). But beyond these three largest ecosystems, many others are worth it. And that’s something we advise to board members we meet: you should keep an eye on what is happening beyond your domestic market, wherever you are based in Europe. Spain has long been very active, Italy is gaining momentum recently, the Nordics enjoy regular InsurTech players, while Benelux has already famous names on its ground (think of Qover in Belgium, Friss in the Netherlands or Ibisa Insurance in Luxembourg). Eastern Europe is very active too, with very strong teams. And you may remember that Quantee - from Poland - got acquired by Guidewire in the first half of 2025 !If insurers truly have less useful customer data than tech platforms or Big Tech, is there a future where those platforms dominate insurance distribution? And what’s the single biggest mindset shift incumbents need to make to benefit from this second wave of innovation rather than be left behind?I really enjoy that topic. On one hand, I remember the early days of InsurTech when the market spoke about “the Uber of insurance”. Then, Google or Amazon gave it a try to insurance and resumed their initiatives. These failed attempts seemed like tech giants could not enter insurance. In the meantime, several have done great in Financial Services (e.g. banking). And beyond these few players - the tech giants - there are plenty of vertical platforms which have significant customer bases in their niche. These players are highly relevant to push insurance to their customers. And actually many already offer insurance solutions. This is enabled by InsurTech players operating in the “embedded insurance” field. They have developed technology enabling any third party to become an insurance distributor. Which scale could these players reach? This is another question. Let’s have a look at eCommerce figures: it accounts for ~30% of all retail spendings. Online insurance distribution might reach such a market share in the future. Embedded insurance is one way to do it, alongside direct distribution. Let’s see where it lands. At least, I doubt insurance could be the only industry worldwide to remain fully offline…Looking ahead, what’s the single biggest mindset shift incumbents need to make if they want to benefit from this second wave of insurance innovation rather than be left behind?I would refer to the “make or buy” dilemma.This is a real pattern I’ve spotted while investing in InsurTech for 10 years (first at AXA Ventures, then at astoryaVC). Incumbents tend to make things first. Whatever the tech trend (note this applies well to the current AI wave). For many reasons - starting with the challenge to attract, and most of all to keep, tech talents - incumbents often fail in their internal initiatives. Ultimately, they come back to the market and partner / buy an external solution. This means there is one way to take the lead and stay 24 to 36 months ahead of your competitors: go directly to external solutions.Of course, there is no one-size-fits-all rule. It’s a matter of choosing the right path: “make” where you do have a competitive advantage ; “buy” elsewhere. Too often, the market tends to “make” on every topic. This should be more balanced. Fortunately, the market is big enough to see several incumbents “buy”, building a competitive advantage by teaming up together with a startup on a specific use-case !]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Kemal now uses a LRU Cache for Faster Routing Performance</title><link>https://old.reddit.com/r/crystal_programming/comments/1olhfag/kemal_now_uses_a_lru_cache_for_faster_routing/</link><author>/u/sdogruyol</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Sat, 1 Nov 2025 07:04:05 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://old.reddit.com/r/crystal_programming/">r/crystal_programming</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Annother Spinoff Shard: ralsina/rate_limiter</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/annother-spinoff-shard-ralsina-rate-limiter/8525</link><author>ralsina</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 22:19:19 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[I am sorry, I know I create a lot of topics all at once, but it happens when I actually have some time to work on my projects Basically, it’s a generic in-memory sliding window composible rate limiter. Usage looks like this:# Per user rate limiting
user_limiter = RateLimiter.new(50, 3600)  # 50 requests per hour per user

# Per IP rate limiting
ip_limiter = RateLimiter.new(200, 3600)  # 200 requests per hour per IP

# Per endpoint rate limiting
endpoint_limiter = RateLimiter.new(20, 60)  # 20 requests per minute per endpoint

# Per user + endpoint rate limiting
user_endpoint_limiter = RateLimiter.new(10, 60)  # 10 requests per minute per user+endpoint

# Check request (example: user trying to access API)
username = "alice"
ip = "10.0.0.1"
endpoint = "/api/create_note"

# Check all applicable rate limits
limits = [
  user_limiter.allow?(username),
  ip_limiter.allow?(ip),
  endpoint_limiter.allow?(endpoint),
  user_endpoint_limiter.allow?("#{username}::#{endpoint}")
]

if limits.any?
  # Request is allowed by all rate limiters
  process_request(username, ip, endpoint)
else
  # Request exceeds at least one rate limit
  render_error("Rate limit exceeded")
end
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Some performance testing</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/some-performance-testing/8524</link><author>ralsina</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 20:04:30 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[As I worked on ToCry I got curious about how well it performed.It was  built with performance as the main goal. In fact it’s sort of guaranteed not to be the fastest way to do things. It uses sepia as data storage, which is the opposite of efficient, and I implemented it .On the other hand, the best thing was to just write some scripts and measure things!Turns out … it’s pretty fast? It can have about 20 simultaneous users and 300 RPS on a Pi 4 with 4GB of RAM, and industry standard says that equates to about 200 users.200 users? On an old SBC! This is not scientific. What a “realistic” load is needs to be discovered by having actual users :-)]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Second fiber does not complete</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/second-fiber-does-not-complete/8523</link><author>axd99</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 16:49:59 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[Hi, I am experimenting with crystal’s fibers and to test with a buffered channel I wrote this:# generate a list of file names.
# This is the data source.
list = [] of String
(1..4).each do |i|
  list << "file#{i}"
end

# provides communication between the producing fiber and the
# consuming one.
ch = Channel(String).new(3)

# fiber1
# this fiber loads the data into the channel
# This is the producer.
spawn do
  puts "--- Entering fiber1"
  list.each do |val|
    puts "fiber1, before send #{val}"
    ch.send val
    puts "fiber1, after send #{val}"
  end
  puts "--- Exiting fiber1"
end

# fiber2
# this fiber empties the channel
# This is the consumer.
spawn do
  puts "---- Entering fiber 2"
  while val2 = ch.receive
    puts "Received: #{val2}"
  end
  puts "---------------------"   # The code does not get to here
  puts "---- Exiting fiber2"
  puts "---------------------"
end

puts "Starting...\n"

# Start the fibers
Fiber.yield

# When the control gets back here all data has been exhausted.
puts "Goodbye!!!"

# shouldn't either of these 2 restart fiber2?
Fiber.yield
ch.close 
p ch.closed?


Now, when I run the above, all data is produced and consumed as expected.
However the ‘---- Exiting Fiber 2’ never executed.$ crystal list-files.cr
Starting...
--- Entering fiber1
fiber1, before send file1
fiber1, after send file1
fiber1, before send file2
fiber1, after send file2
fiber1, before send file3
fiber1, after send file3
fiber1, before send file4
---- Entering fiber 2
Received: file1
Received: file2
Received: file3
Received: file4
fiber1, after send file4
--- Exiting fiber1
Goodbye!!!
true
Any pointer would be most welcome.
Many thanks.]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Wanna do an MCP? Try this :-)</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/wanna-do-an-mcp-try-this/8520</link><author>ralsina</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 19:46:53 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[MCP is a mechanism to expose things to AI agents.Turns out it’s super easy to do, and it gives you some amazing leverage for tools! For example, I gave my kanban board a MCP server and now I can just say “move the note “whatever” to done” and it works ;-)It supports stdio MCP servers (nice way to expose a CLI tool to AI agents) and web MCP servers (with kemal at least)Here is a FULL example of a MCP with a single tool, in stdio mode:require "mcp"

# A simple tool that returns the answer to any question
class AnswerTool < MCP::AbstractTool
  @@tool_name = "get_answer"
  @@tool_description = "Returns 42 as the answer to any question you ask"
  @@tool_input_schema = {
    "type"       => "object",
    "properties" => {
      "question" => {
        "type"        => "string",
        "description" => "The question you want answered",
      },
    },
    "required" => ["question"],
  }.to_json

  def invoke(params : Hash(String, JSON::Any), env : HTTP::Server::Context? = nil)
    question = params["question"]?.try(&.as_s) || "unknown question"
    {
      "answer"   => 42,
      "question" => question,
    }
  end
end

# Start the stdio server - that's it! One line and you have a complete MCP server.
MCP::StdioHandler.start_server
Have fun and let me know if something is not ergnomic, I am trying to make this as boilerplate-free as possible.14 posts - 6 participants]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Airsailer - open source Cloud orchestrator in Crystal</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/airsailer-open-source-cloud-orchestrator-in-crystal/8516</link><author>paulocoghi</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 09:45:44 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[Missed you all during my cancer treatment, and I’m finally cancer-free!I’m back full-time at my cloud computing startup, and going fully open source (MIT license) for the entire platform.LXC (Linux/system containers) for bare-metal performance, no VM overhead (PoC working)elastic bare-metal hardware resources that can be changed without rebootelastic LVM storage with thin-provisioning (manually handled today)routing for local networks + WireGuard for clusters (manually handled today)Homogeneous deployment as the strategy for automatic horizontal scaling and load-balancing (will be on a future release with PaaS automation)automatic proxy + SSL for apps, no need for 1 public IP per app (proxy lib temporarily made in JS because of acme-client lib) IaaS+PaaS with 20% of features that cover 80% of cloud demand.I’m refactoring and I will release soon at github.com/airsailer/airsailer. Since I sustain my family only through this work, I expect to release a new production version soon.Happy to talk to you again. ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Crystal Prime Deluxe 18000 Box of 10</title><link>https://dev.to/crystalprimedeluxe18000boxof10/crystal-prime-deluxe-18000-box-of-10-5gkf</link><author>Crystal Prime Deluxe 18000 Box of 10</author><category>blog</category><pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 16:09:54 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://dev.to/t/crystal">DEV Community: crystal</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[VapeZone  offers premium vape products at competitive prices, based in the UK. Explore our wide range of high-quality vapes and accessories.]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Inside an Isotemp OCXO107-10 Oven Controlled Crystal Oscillator</title><link>https://tomverbeure.github.io/2025/10/26/Inside-an-Isotemp-OCXO107-10.html</link><author>zdw</author><category>HN</category><category>hn</category><pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 21:35:46 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://news.ycombinator.com/newest">Hacker News - Newest: &quot;Crystal&quot;</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Create parsor for simple if statements</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/create-parsor-for-simple-if-statements/8514</link><author>Fulgurance</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 17:18:02 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[Hi guys, I am seeking help/advice to make a very simple parser that use just  statement (I mean not with  statement or )I did already a condition parser that work, but I don’t know how to manage if there is multiple if.Basically, when my parser read a configuration file, I would like when it parse it to read the if statements:if (condition)
    if (condition)
        (do this)
    end
    if (condition)
        (do this)
    end
end
How can I manage this ? I tried to put the problem on paper, find a way, but I actually don’t really find a solution. If someone have experience already with this, I will be gratefulIn my example, if you are in the last condition, how can I know if I am not under the previous one ?]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Inside an Isotemp OCXO107-10 Oven Controlled Crystal Oscillator</title><link>https://tomverbeure.github.io/2025/10/26/Inside-an-Isotemp-OCXO107-10.html</link><author>thomasjb</author><category>HN</category><category>hn</category><pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 10:17:24 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://news.ycombinator.com/newest">Hacker News - Newest: &quot;Crystal&quot;</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Cml and choose - type problems</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/cml-and-choose-type-problems/8509</link><author>dsisnero</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2025 08:13:37 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[# =============================================================================
# Concurrent ML `choose` type inference problem in Crystal
# =============================================================================
#
# This document describes a real-world type inference limitation encountered
# when porting John Reppy’s Concurrent ML (CML) design to Crystal language.
#
# The CML model centers on *events* (values of type `Event(T)`), which represent
# potential synchronous communications or computations.  Multiple events can
# be combined using `choose_evt` (nondeterministic choice), and only one branch
# “commits” when synchronized via `sync(evt)`.
#
# The core invariant:  `choose` is purely a combinator; it doesn’t perform
# until `sync` is called.  This design works well in SML because its type
# inference engine easily unifies all branch result types, and events such as
# `timeout_evt` or `never_evt` can safely coexist in a single choice.
#
# In Crystal, we’re very close — but there’s a key *type inference barrier*:
#
# -----------------------------------------------------------------------------
# Problem Summary
# -----------------------------------------------------------------------------
#
# When combining heterogeneous `Event(T)` types in an `Array`, Crystal’s type
# inference produces a union of the *concrete generic instantiations* rather
# than a single polymorphic supertype.  This breaks overload resolution for a
# method like:
#
#     def self.choose(evts : Array(Event(T))) : Event(T) forall T
#
# Example:
#
#     ch = CML::Chan(Int32).new
#
#     choice = CML.choose([
#       CML.wrap(ch.recv_evt) { |_| :recv },              # Event(Symbol)
#       CML.wrap(CML.timeout(0.1.seconds)) { |_| :timeout }, # Event(Symbol)
#     ])
#
#     # ❌ Compiler error:
#     # expected Array(Event(Symbol)), not Array(Event(Symbol) | TimeoutEvt)
#
# Even though all branches *conceptually* yield `Symbol`, Crystal’s invariance
# and separate generic instantiations mean it cannot unify them automatically.
#
# In SML, this works because type inference is polymorphic by default:
#    val e1 : ’a event
#    val e2 : unit event
#    val choice = choose [wrap e1 (fn _ => #recv), wrap timeout_event (fn _ => #timeout)]
#
# -----------------------------------------------------------------------------
# Why `never` and `timeout` amplify the issue
# -----------------------------------------------------------------------------
#
# - `never_evt` is typed as `Event(T)` but never produces a value — it’s inert.
#   In ML, this freely unifies with anything (like `’a event`).
# - `timeout_evt` naturally yields a `Symbol` (`:timeout`) or unit.
#   In practice, most real `choose` calls race real events against a timeout.
#
# In Crystal, these must share a single `T` type parameter in
# `Array(Event(T))`, but the compiler cannot infer it when generics differ.
#
# -----------------------------------------------------------------------------
# Workarounds tried
# -----------------------------------------------------------------------------
#
# 1. Manual casting:
#
#        typed_never = CML.wrap(CML.never(Int32)) { |_| :never } as CML::Event(Symbol)
#        choice = CML.choose([typed_never,
#                             CML.wrap(ch.recv_evt) { |_| :recv },
#                             CML.wrap(CML.timeout(0.1.seconds)) { |_| :timeout }])
#
#    ✅ Works, but ugly and non-obvious for library users.
#
# 2. Force the array literal type explicitly:
#
#        choice = CML.choose([
#          CML.wrap(CML.never(Int32)) { |_| :never },
#          CML.wrap(ch.recv_evt) { |_| :recv },
#          CML.wrap(CML.timeout(0.1.seconds)) { |_| :timeout },
#        ] of CML::Event(Symbol))
#
#    ✅ Works, but verbose and not ergonomic.
#
# 3. A dynamic fallback (library side):
#
#        def self.choose_any(evts : Array(Event) | Tuple)
#          unified = evts.map do |e|
#            CML.wrap(e.as(Event)) { |x| x.as(Symbol | Nil | Int32 | String) }
#          end
#          ChooseEvt(Symbol | Nil | Int32 | String).new(unified)
#        end
#
#    ✅ Works, allows mixing `TimeoutEvt` and others.
#    ⚠️ Loses static type guarantees, since all results are widened into a big union.
#
# -----------------------------------------------------------------------------
# Desired behavior
# -----------------------------------------------------------------------------
#
# Ideally, Crystal could unify the type variable `T` across generic parameters
# of `Event(T)` when placed in an array, producing something like:
#
#     Array(Event(Symbol))  ← rather than  Array(Event(Symbol) | TimeoutEvt)
#
# That would allow:
#
#     choice = CML.choose([
#       CML.wrap(ch.recv_evt) { |_| :recv },
#       CML.wrap(CML.timeout(0.1.seconds)) { |_| :timeout },
#       CML.never(Int32)
#     ])
#     result = CML.sync(choice)
#
# to compile cleanly.
#
# -----------------------------------------------------------------------------
# Minimal Repro
# -----------------------------------------------------------------------------
#
# ```crystal
# module CML
#   abstract class Event(T); end
#
#   class TimeoutEvt < Event(Symbol); end
#   class RecvEvt(T) < Event(T); end
#
#   def self.choose(evts : Array(Event(T))) : Event(T) forall T
#     # no-op
#     evts.first
#   end
# end
#
# ch = CML::RecvEvt(Int32).new
# choice = CML.choose([ch, CML::TimeoutEvt.new])
# ```
#
# ❌ Error: expected argument #1 to 'choose' to be Array(Event(Int32)), not Array(Event(Int32) | CML::TimeoutEvt)
#
# -----------------------------------------------------------------------------
# Discussion questions for Crystal core / type system developers
# -----------------------------------------------------------------------------
#
# 1. Could Crystal’s generic unification rules be relaxed to allow
#    `Array(Event(Int32) | Event(Symbol))` to unify as `Array(Event(Int32 | Symbol))`
#    when the same generic base type is used?
#
# 2. Is there a way for a library to express a “variance-like” constraint
#    on generic parameters for this pattern — e.g., `Event` being covariant in `T`?
#
# 3. Would a macro-level solution (`macro choose_evt(*evts)`) be able to
#    introspect and compute a common union type of the block return values,
#    producing an `Array(Event(common_union_type))` automatically?
#
# 4. Is there any pattern or compiler hint (`.splat`, `typeof(...)`) that can
#    achieve this statically today without resorting to a huge union wrapper?
#
# -----------------------------------------------------------------------------
# The goal
# -----------------------------------------------------------------------------
#
# Bring Crystal’s ergonomics for typed event combinators closer to the
# Concurrent ML model:
#
#     choose [timeout_evt, recv_evt, never_evt] |> sync
#
# should “just work” without any explicit type coercion,
# while retaining static safety and type inference fidelity.
#
# -----------------------------------------------------------------------------
# Thank you!
# -----------------------------------------------------------------------------
#
# Any insight or future direction for generic covariance, inference improvements,
# or macro-based workarounds would be incredibly valuable for Crystal libraries
# that implement higher-level concurrency abstractions like Concurrent ML.
#
# -- Dominic Sisneros (dsisnero)
# -----------------------------------------------------------------------------

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Equivalent of Ruby&apos;s `self.class::Subclass`</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/equivalent-of-rubys-self-class-subclass/8508</link><author>Cristian</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 21:08:32 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[I would like to convert this Ruby code to Crystal:# Ruby code

class P
  class Sub
    def m
      "from P::Sub"
    end
  end
  
  def sub_m
    self.class::Sub.new.m
  end
end


class C < P
  class Sub
    def m
      "from C::Sub"
    end
  end
end


puts C.new.sub_m # => "from C::Sub"

By using ,  returns “from C::Sub” instead of “from P::Sub”, but this syntax is not valid in Crystal: Error: unexpected token: "::"17 posts - 7 participants]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>How can I force the type of a nested literal from the outside in?</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/how-can-i-force-the-type-of-a-nested-literal-from-the-outside-in/8507</link><author>Carlos</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 18:58:28 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[I want an array of , buticr:1> typeof([["str"], [:sym], ["str", :sym]])
 => Array(Array(String | Symbol) | Array(String) | Array(Symbol))
I can force the type of the inner arraysicr:2> typeof([["str"] of String | Symbol, [:sym] of String | Symbol, ["str", :sym]])
 => Array(Array(String | Symbol))
but I’d rather not do that, because that’s a lot of typing. I’d rather doicr:3> typeof([["str"], [:sym], ["str", :sym]] of Array(String | Symbol))
error in line 1
Error: instantiating 'Pointer(Array(String | Symbol))#[]=(Int32, Array(String))'


In C:\Users\carlo\scoop\apps\crystal\current\src\pointer.cr:146:29

 146 | (self + offset).value = value
                               ^----
Error: type must be Array(String | Symbol), not Array(String)
Shouldn’t the compiler propagate the type specification, not only from the inside out, but also from the outside in?]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Feasibility of multi-executable architecture for a large application using Crystal</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/feasibility-of-multi-executable-architecture-for-a-large-application-using-crystal/8505</link><author>gauravshah89</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 10:32:33 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[Crystal is my most-loved language  and I have been using it for small personal projects on and off. I am now starting a new project that may not remain personal in the long-run and should eventually grow on to become a large and complex desktop app. Run time performance will be a key requirement for this application.Since crystal has higher compile times compared to other languages, what is the best way to create very large and performant applications using crystal without getting bogged down by compile times?My Strategy  => Split the application into smaller  built from shared libraries rather than one monolithic Crystal binary. Rough proposed file structure given below: will be a standalone Crystal app/lib  () that compile quickly and will be linked to each other.common/
shard.yml         # shared library (types, utils)api/
shard.yml         # depends on ../commonworker/
shard.yml         # depends on ../commoncli/
shard.yml         # minimal dependenciesIs this a scalable approach for developing and maintaining serious production applications in Crystal? If this does not work out, I will have to use Rust which I don’t prefer.Thanks for reading this long question. ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>A Closer Look at Piezoelectric Crystal</title><link>https://www.samaterials.com/content/a-closer-look-at-stressed-piezo-crystals.html</link><author>pillars</author><category>HN</category><category>hn</category><pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 16:12:16 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://news.ycombinator.com/newest">Hacker News - Newest: &quot;Crystal&quot;</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[
                        Last updated on {{lastDate}}                    ²]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>We&apos;re reaching for the stars! 🚀✨</title><link>https://fosstodon.org/@CrystalLanguage/115418209673688930</link><author></author><category>official</category><enclosure url="https://cdn.fosstodon.org/media_attachments/files/115/418/195/353/117/484/original/d2be7cb66f9956a5.png" length="" type="text/plain"/><pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 14:08:35 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://fosstodon.org/@CrystalLanguage">@CrystalLanguage</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[We're reaching for the stars! 🚀✨Just as 1.18 is released, over 20k users have starred the Crystal repo on GitHub 🌟]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Crystal 1.18.2 is released!</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/crystal-1-18-2-is-released/8504</link><author>Crys</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 20:20:55 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[We are announcing a new Crystal release 1.18.2 with two regressions fixed.]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>LSP implementation for Crystal on Windows</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/lsp-implementation-for-crystal-on-windows/8502</link><author>god</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 12:02:42 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[The tooling for Crystal on Windows is not good. I am working on a language server and VSCode extension that leverages the existing CLI tools available and incorporates them into an instant-response context so as to achieve features such as autocomplete, real-time error detection, etc… on Windows, since Crystalline and Scry seem to be for POSIX platforms only.Demo of its current capabilities can be observed hereSource code is here, you can build the vsix for the vscode extension with “npm run package”, and the server itself with “shards build”.]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Crystal 1.18.2 is released!</title><link>https://crystal-lang.org/2025/10/21/1.18.2-released/</link><author>Johannes Müller</author><category>releases</category><pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://crystal-lang.org/">Releases</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[We are announcing a new Crystal release 1.18.2 with two regressions fixed.This release includes 3 changes since
1.18.1
by 3 contributors.  We thank all the contributors for all the effort put into
improving the language! ❤️This patch release fixes a regression in the type restrictions of
 (#16231), and a bug in
Fiber::ExecutionContext.default_workers_count (#16227) - both errors were
introduced in 1.18.0.We have been able to do all of this thanks to the continued support of
 84codes and every other sponsor.  To
 maintain and increase the development pace, donations and sponsorships are
 essential.  OpenCollective is
 available for that.Reach out to crystal@manas.tech if you’d like to
 become a direct sponsor or find other ways to support Crystal. We thank you in
 advance!Contribute]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Optimization for nillable var check and code</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/optimization-for-nillable-var-check-and-code/8501</link><author>AlexR</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 22:57:22 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[Is there something terser than this:getter tex : LibSDL::Texture*?

def render
  tex = @tex
  return unless tex
  LibSDL.set_texture_alpha_mod(tex, 255)
  ...
end
Original code, rejected by the compiler, being :getter tex : LibSDL::Texture*?

def render
  LibSDL.set_texture_alpha_mod(@tex.as(LibSDL::texture*), 255) if @tex
  ...
end

# compilation error
# Error: can't cast (Pointer(LibSDL::Texture) | Nil) to Pointer(LibSDL::Texture)
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Crystal 1.18.1 is Released!</title><link>https://old.reddit.com/r/crystal_programming/comments/1obocwx/crystal_1181_is_released/</link><author>/u/Meatack</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 17:32:54 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://old.reddit.com/r/crystal_programming/">r/crystal_programming</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[   submitted by    /u/Meatack ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>From Raw Crystal to Crystal Oscillator – Crystals Go to War in 1943</title><link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=duZlWWwxIPQ</link><author>akshatjiwan</author><category>HN</category><category>hn</category><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 17:05:02 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://news.ycombinator.com/newest">Hacker News - Newest: &quot;Crystal&quot;</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Check if an array index exist</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/check-if-an-array-index-exist/8500</link><author>Fulgurance</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2025 20:19:25 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[Hi guys, I am actually coding a parser, and in my program I need to check if an index exist or not in the array. I did this, but when I try to run the code, crystal raise an error that my condition have  an index out of bound, why ?elsif Parser::ElseFilter.matches?(strippedLine)
    if !elsePresence[currentIfLevel-1].nil? && elsePresence[currentIfLevel-1] || elsePresence[currentIfLevel-1].nil?
        puts elsePresence.inspect
        puts currentIfLevel-1
        raise("Line #{index+1}\nFile: #{path}\nExtra else: #{line}\nAn extra \"else\" was declared.")
    end
Normally because I check if it is nil, I should not have problem with my condition no ?]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Ruby controversy - Crystal opportunity</title><link>https://forum.crystal-lang.org/t/ruby-controversy-crystal-opportunity/8498</link><author>dsisnero</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2025 17:41:06 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://forum.crystal-lang.org/latest">Forum</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[@jgaskins With the recent controversy happening in ruby over Ruby Central and also DHH, it might be an opportunity for the more followed Crystal enthusiasts to re-introduce Crystal to the ruby world.10 posts - 6 participants]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>We&apos;ve just released Crystal 1.18.1 - a small bugfix version that solves two regressions.</title><link>https://fosstodon.org/@CrystalLanguage/115391082654527812</link><author></author><category>official</category><pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 19:09:49 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://fosstodon.org/@CrystalLanguage">@CrystalLanguage</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[We've just released Crystal 1.18.1 - a small bugfix version that solves two regressions.]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Crystal 1.18.1 is released!</title><link>https://crystal-lang.org/2025/10/17/1.18.1-released/</link><author>Matias Garcia Isaia</author><category>releases</category><pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://crystal-lang.org/">Releases</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[We are announcing a new Crystal release 1.18.1 with two regressions fixed.This release includes 2 changes since
1.18.0
by 1 contributor.  We thank all the contributors for all the effort put into
improving the language! ❤️This patch release fixes a regression in the  def parsing (#16217), and
overly strict type restrictions in  (#16218) - both introduced
in 1.18.0.We have been able to do all of this thanks to the continued support of
 84codes and every other sponsor.  To
 maintain and increase the development pace, donations and sponsorships are
 essential.  OpenCollective is
 available for that.Reach out to crystal@manas.tech if you’d like to
 become a direct sponsor or find other ways to support Crystal. We thank you in
 advance!Contribute]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Crystal 1.18.0 Is Released</title><link>https://crystal-lang.org/2025/10/14/1.18.0-released/</link><author>sdogruyol</author><category>HN</category><category>hn</category><pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 14:30:44 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://news.ycombinator.com/newest">Hacker News - Newest: &quot;Crystal&quot;</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[We are announcing a new Crystal release 1.18.0 with several new features and bug
fixes.This release includes 172 changes since
1.17.1
by 31 contributors. We thank all the contributors for all the effort put into
improving the language! ❤️Below we list the most remarkable changes in the language, compiler and stdlib.
For more details, visit the full
changelog.We do not expect any breaking changes in existing code. If you notice any
unexpected issues, please let us know in the issue tracker or forum.Execution contexts from RFC 0002 continue as a preview feature with opt-in
with compiler flags -Dpreview_mt -Dexecution_context. It might move out of
preview in the next release.The preview of synchronization primitives in  has seen some
improvements as well.Deprecation warnings are now available on types and aliases (#15962) as well
as individual method parameters (#15999).
Deprecated types only trigger warnings when they are actually  (e.g.
calling a class method), not when they’re just part of a type restriction, for
example.
Deprecated parameters only trigger a warning when the particular parameter is
used in a call. Calls without this parameter are unaffected.The format of  has been adjusted slightly to align with the Internet
Extended Date/Time Format (IXDTF) defined in RFC 9557 (#16039).Changes from the previous format:Replace  location by  offsetSkip zero nanoseconds entirely even when  is true (see https://github.com/crystal-lang/crystal/pull/16039#discussion_r2250863021)Remove whitespace between time and offsetWrap location in square brackets to indicate an IXDTF time-zone suffixSome examples show the differences:The local Windows system time zone now uses the canonical IANA name (#15967).The output of  got a wrapper to indicate
the  type and differentiate from the wrapped type (#15979).
The equivalent for  is still pending.The private constructors of  moved into the 
hook (#16147). They’re now defined on the including types which is more robust
in terms of  overload ordering. This also allows referring generic
type variables inside converters. now uses scoped ANSI reset codes which only reset the respective
property, instead of resetting  (#16052).We added type restrictions to many API methods. This improves the documentation.
This is a semi-automatic effort, assisted by a tool that automatically extracts
typing information from the semantic analysis of a program (#15682).Multi-line strings containing source code in compiler specs have had two
different formats: Some of them were using regular string literals, others used
heredocs. The latter was usually preferred in new code additions because
line numbers and indents are more sensible. And with an appropriate heredoc
identifier to denote the language, we even get nested syntax highlighting.
In this release we’ve converted all compiler specs to use heredocs
(#11291).With the help of , we’ve enabled and applied a couple more linter rules:
 (#16010),  (#16011), and
 (#16014).The compiler can dump type information to a JSON file when the environment
variable  is set (#16027).Resolve types when guessing return type from class method overloads (#16118).In the following snippet, the compiler is able to infer ’s type to be , since both overloads of  have a return type of :Guess instance variable types from global method calls (#16119).This allows the following to compile:The call needs to be global; other than that, type guessing for top-level methods has the same limitations as for class methods.Hash literals are evaluated from left to right, fixing a regression from 1.6.0 (#16124).Temporary variables are now grouped by file name in order to increase the chance
of reusing previous macro expansions (#16122).Fully exit the process on  from REPL (#16171)Fixed interpreter hanging on the signal pipe (#16167)Support for LLVM 21.1 and 22.0 (#16062)Update Unicode to 17.0.0 (#16160)We have been able to do all of this thanks to the continued support of
 84codes and every other sponsor.  To
 maintain and increase the development pace, donations and sponsorships are
 essential.  OpenCollective is
 available for that.Reach out to crystal@manas.tech if you’d like to
 become a direct sponsor or find other ways to support Crystal. We thank you in
 advance!Contribute]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Crystal 1.18.0 is released!</title><link>https://old.reddit.com/r/crystal_programming/comments/1o7ckdv/crystal_1180_is_released/</link><author>/u/sdogruyol</author><category>community</category><pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 14:29:46 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://old.reddit.com/r/crystal_programming/">r/crystal_programming</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Notes on Building CLI and GUI tools with Crystal</title><link>https://dev.to/kojix2/notes-on-building-cli-and-gui-tools-with-crystal-4pcd</link><author>kojix2</author><category>blog</category><pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 03:25:14 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://dev.to/t/crystal">DEV Community: crystal</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[This post is just me writing down some vague thoughts that are floating around in my head right now.Sorry if you came here expecting a well-structured tutorial — but you know, if I try to organize everything perfectly, I’ll never publish anything.Crystal originated from the Ruby community, so there are many people who want to build web applications with it.However, the Crystal programming language itself can be described as “a statically compiled language with a Ruby-like syntax and a garbage collector, somewhat like C with GC and type inference.”It’s not necessarily optimized for web applications.Personally, I wanted to use Crystal for command-line tools and GUI apps.For some reason, though, there don’t seem to be many people building CLI tools in Crystal.The ecosystem for building and distributing binaries wasn’t very well developed for a long time.That used to be a real pain, but after gradually solving those issues, I think we’re now at the point where most CLI tools I want can be built and distributed in Crystal without much trouble.On the GUI side, the situation is similar — there aren’t many libraries available.But this isn’t unique to Crystal. GUI programming, in general, depends heavily on opaque, platform-specific APIs, which don’t always play nicely with open-source development.Then I got curious about Tauri and Electron — the now-famous WebView-based app frameworks.Personally, I can barely read JavaScript, so I had no real interest in those at first, but their popularity made me curious.And as I mentioned earlier, web app development in the Crystal ecosystem is quite active.So I decided to give it a try.I learned that “WebView” isn’t a single library — each OS (Windows, Linux, macOS) provides its own.Projects like webview/webview and Tauri’s wry act as unifying layers over these platform-specific APIs.Tauri itself uses WebView under the hood while also providing a framework to handle security and integration with Rust backends.Maybe it’s possible to use TypeScript and other frontend tools with Crystal too, but personally, I prefer the more old-fashioned approach — something like Kemal + ECR, the “classic amateur” way.When I actually started building an app with Crystal + WebView, I discovered a few things.First, you need to pay attention to event loops and thread management.The WebView itself runs in a separate process, and at the same time you need to run a Kemal server.That means you often have to make it multithreaded and carefully manage your execution contexts or Fibers — otherwise, things simply won’t run correctly.Then there’s the build, linking, and packaging pain.I sent a few pull requests to the Crystal WebView project, which helped a bit, but building on MinGW is still rough.MSVC technically works, but it’s just too tedious to deal with, so I decided to stay away from it.Bundling shared libraries is also tricky.I’d prefer to lean toward static linking whenever possible, but depending on licensing and security update concerns, it’s sometimes better to link against system or bundled shared libraries.I discovered tools like fpm, which are really useful, but in the end, I still end up asking AI to help me write custom GitHub Actions YAML and shell scripts.And then, once you finally have a working binary, Windows or macOS antivirus software will happily flag it as suspicious.Maybe for people doing this professionally, all this doesn’t sound like a big deal, but as someone doing it for fun, it’s a lot of work.
Even so, after all the pain, I’ve started to feel like — maybe, just maybe — this setup is actually pretty cool.This post was translated from the original Japanese version using ChatGPT.
You can read the original post here [JA]]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Extra, extra - Crystal 1.18.0 is out now!</title><link>https://fosstodon.org/@CrystalLanguage/115374378935720511</link><author></author><category>official</category><pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 20:21:51 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://fosstodon.org/@CrystalLanguage">@CrystalLanguage</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[Extra, extra - Crystal 1.18.0 is out now!]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>How a quartz crystal works in a microcontroller?</title><link>https://dev.to/carolineee/how-a-quartz-crystal-works-in-a-microcontroller-4lhf</link><author>Hedy</author><category>blog</category><pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 09:37:43 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://dev.to/t/crystal">DEV Community: crystal</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[This is a fundamental concept in microcontroller systems. Let's break down how a quartz crystal works in a microcontroller, from the basic physics to the practical circuit.The Core Concept: The Piezoelectric Effect
At the heart of a quartz crystal is a physical phenomenon called the Piezoelectric Effect.Mechanical → Electrical: When you apply a physical stress (squeeze or bend) to a quartz crystal, it generates a small electrical voltage across its surfaces.Electrical → Mechanical: Conversely, when you apply an electrical voltage to a quartz crystal, it physically deforms (vibrates) slightly.This two-way street is the magic key.How It Creates a Clock Signal: ResonanceNatural Frequency: Every piece of quartz crystal has a natural resonant frequency—a specific frequency at which it "likes" to vibrate most efficiently. This frequency is determined primarily by its physical size, shape, and how it's cut. A thinner, smaller crystal vibrates at a higher frequency. This is why crystals for common microcontrollers (like 16 MHz, 20 MHz) are small, while crystals for real-time clocks (32.768 kHz) are larger and often cylindrical.The Oscillator Circuit: Inside the microcontroller, there is a specialized circuit called a Crystal Oscillator (often denoted as OSC1 and OSC2 pins). This circuit is designed to:Apply a constantly alternating voltage to the crystal.Listen to the tiny voltage generated by the crystal's vibration.Amplify that signal and feed it back to the crystal.The Self-Sustaining Loop (The "How It Works"):When you power on the circuit, electrical noise provides a tiny, random voltage kick to the crystal.The crystal vibrates in response, generating a tiny voltage at its natural resonant frequency.The oscillator circuit in the microcontroller picks up this tiny signal, amplifies it, and feeds it back to the crystal.This reinforced signal causes the crystal to vibrate more strongly.Within a few milliseconds, this feedback loop builds up into a strong, continuous, and perfectly stable oscillation at the crystal's precise natural frequency.The result is a clean, square-wave clock signal that drives the entire microcontroller.The Complete Picture: The Practical Circuit
On your schematic and PCB, you don't just connect the crystal directly to the MCU. A typical crystal circuit looks like this:text

         ---||---       ---||---
OSC1 |---|     |---X---|     |---| OSC2
     |    C1        |        C2   |
     |              |             |
     |-------------/ \------------|
                   Rf (Internal)
Illustration of a typical crystal oscillator circuitComponents and Their Roles:Quartz Crystal (X): The resonant element that sets the frequency.Load Capacitors (C1 and C2): These are absolutely critical.Purpose: They, along with the crystal's own internal capacitance, form a capacitive load that helps the crystal oscillate at its specified frequency.Value: The values (typically 10-22 pF for most MCUs) are chosen to match the crystal's specified load capacitance. Using the wrong values can make the oscillator unstable or cause the frequency to be slightly off.Internal Oscillator Circuit (inside MCU): Contains the amplifier and a feedback resistor (Rf), which biases the amplifier into its linear region so it can start and maintain oscillation.Why is the Clock Signal So Important?
The clock signal is the "heartbeat" of the microcontroller. It synchronizes every operation:Core Execution: The CPU executes instructions in time with the clock ticks (each tick is one clock cycle).Peripheral Timing: Timers, PWM (Pulse Width Modulation), and communication interfaces like UART, SPI, and I2C all rely on the clock to generate precise baud rates and time intervals.Bus Operations: Reading from Flash memory, writing to RAM, and accessing peripherals are all coordinated by the clock.A simple analogy: Imagine an orchestra without a conductor. It would be chaotic. The crystal-generated clock signal is the conductor, ensuring every part of the microcontroller works in perfect synchrony.The Special 32.768 kHz "Watch Crystal"
You often see a second, smaller crystal on boards (shaped like a tiny can). This is almost always a 32.768 kHz crystal.Why that number? 32,768 = 2¹⁵.A simple 15-stage binary divider circuit can easily divide this frequency down to exactly 1 Hz (one pulse per second), which is perfect for driving a Real-Time Clock (RTC) to keep track of time, even when the main microcontroller is in sleep mode.It's a resonator: The quartz crystal doesn't create a frequency out of nothing; it filters and stabilizes the oscillation to its precise natural frequency.Piezoelectric Effect is key: The mechanical-electrical feedback loop is what makes it work.It's a system: The crystal alone won't work. It needs the microcontroller's internal oscillator circuit and the external load capacitors to form a complete, functioning oscillator.Precision and Stability: Compared to internal RC oscillators, crystals are vastly more accurate and stable over temperature and voltage changes, which is essential for timing-critical applications and communication protocols.]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Crystal 1.18.0 is released!</title><link>https://crystal-lang.org/2025/10/14/1.18.0-released/</link><author>Johannes Müller</author><category>releases</category><pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><source url="https://crystal-lang.org/">Releases</source><content:encoded><![CDATA[We are announcing a new Crystal release 1.18.0 with several new features and bug
fixes.This release includes 172 changes since
1.17.1
by 31 contributors. We thank all the contributors for all the effort put into
improving the language! ❤️Below we list the most remarkable changes in the language, compiler and stdlib.
For more details, visit the full
changelog.We do not expect any breaking changes in existing code. If you notice any
unexpected issues, please let us know in the issue tracker or forum.Execution contexts from RFC 0002 continue as a preview feature with opt-in
with compiler flags -Dpreview_mt -Dexecution_context. It might move out of
preview in the next release.The preview of synchronization primitives in  has seen some
improvements as well.Deprecation warnings are now available on types and aliases (#15962) as well
as individual method parameters (#15999).
Deprecated types only trigger warnings when they are actually  (e.g.
calling a class method), not when they’re just part of a type restriction, for
example.
Deprecated parameters only trigger a warning when the particular parameter is
used in a call. Calls without this parameter are unaffected.The format of  has been adjusted slightly to align with the Internet
Extended Date/Time Format (IXDTF) defined in RFC 9557 (#16039).Changes from the previous format:Replace  location by  offsetSkip zero nanoseconds entirely even when  is true (see https://github.com/crystal-lang/crystal/pull/16039#discussion_r2250863021)Remove whitespace between time and offsetWrap location in square brackets to indicate an IXDTF time-zone suffixSome examples show the differences:The local Windows system time zone now uses the canonical IANA name (#15967).The output of  got a wrapper to indicate
the  type and differentiate from the wrapped type (#15979).
The equivalent for  is still pending.The private constructors of  moved into the 
hook (#16147). They’re now defined on the including types which is more robust
in terms of  overload ordering. This also allows referring generic
type variables inside converters. now uses scoped ANSI reset codes which only reset the respective
property, instead of resetting  (#16052).We added type restrictions to many API methods. This improves the documentation.
This is a semi-automatic effort, assisted by a tool that automatically extracts
typing information from the semantic analysis of a program (#15682).Multi-line strings containing source code in compiler specs have had two
different formats: Some of them were using regular string literals, others used
heredocs. The latter was usually preferred in new code additions because
line numbers and indents are more sensible. And with an appropriate heredoc
identifier to denote the language, we even get nested syntax highlighting.
In this release we’ve converted all compiler specs to use heredocs
(#11291).With the help of , we’ve enabled and applied a couple more linter rules:
 (#16010),  (#16011), and
 (#16014).The compiler can dump type information to a JSON file when the environment
variable  is set (#16027).Resolve types when guessing return type from class method overloads (#16118).In the following snippet, the compiler is able to infer ’s type to be , since both overloads of  have a return type of :Guess instance variable types from global method calls (#16119).This allows the following to compile:The call needs to be global; other than that, type guessing for top-level methods has the same limitations as for class methods.Hash literals are evaluated from left to right, fixing a regression from 1.6.0 (#16124).Temporary variables are now grouped by file name in order to increase the chance
of reusing previous macro expansions (#16122).Fully exit the process on  from REPL (#16171)Fixed interpreter hanging on the signal pipe (#16167)Support for LLVM 21.1 and 22.0 (#16062)Update Unicode to 17.0.0 (#16160)We have been able to do all of this thanks to the continued support of
 84codes and every other sponsor.  To
 maintain and increase the development pace, donations and sponsorships are
 essential.  OpenCollective is
 available for that.Reach out to crystal@manas.tech if you’d like to
 become a direct sponsor or find other ways to support Crystal. We thank you in
 advance!Contribute]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>